Finding Aid for Daniel Cherrin papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Daniel Cherrin papers 2008-2009
Cherrin, Daniel.
2015026 Aa 3
Press Secretary and Director of Communications for the City of Detroit and Mayor Kenneth Cockrel, Jr. following the resignation of Kwame Kilpatrick. Includes records of finances, official communications and news stories, and Cockrel's work on various initiatives such as support for the auto industry, Cobo Center expansion, Angel's Night, and Detroit's bond ratings.
76.3 MB online
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Daniel Cherrin (donor no. 11250 ), in April 2015.
The collection is open to research.
Daniel Cherrin is an attorney practicing public relations and crisis management who was Press Secretary and Director of Communications for Kenneth V. Cockrel, Jr. during his term as Mayor of Detroit following the resignation of Kwame Kilpatrick. In these roles, Cherrin helped manage the City of Detroit's response to federal loans for the auto industry and Cockrel's efforts to address Detroit's economic problems in the midst of the larger 2008 financial crisis. Cherrin was responsible for creating and implementing strategic communications strategies following the resignation of the previous mayor, the financial collapse of the auto industry, and for events such as the NCAA Final Four, the North American International Auto Show, and the Annual Thanksgiving Day Parade. Cherrin also serves as a mediator, focusing on public policy disputes.
Cherrin has provided strategic communications and public affairs consulting to Fortune 500 companies, universities, international border crossings, mayors, venture-backed start-ups, and non-profits including The New York Times, Detroit Windsor Tunnel, Windsor, Ontario, the University of Windsor, University of Toledo, Wayne State University School of Medicine, Detroit Wayne County Port Authority, Guardian Industries, Vistage International, Starfish Family Services, the Cultural Alliance of Southeastern Michigan, and other organizations.
The founder of North Coast Strategies, a public relations and communications firm, Cherrin has also served as the spokesman for Mackinac Island, Mich., Detroit Bulk Storage and The Ann Arbor Art Fair. He chaired the Executive Leadership Committee for the Michigan Society of Association Executives in 2012-2013. Cherrin has been also involved and served on the Michigan Political Leadership Program Finance Committee and Board of Directors. Cherrin also served on the Board of Directors of the Engineering Society of Detroit (2003-2010) and of the Urban League of Detroit (2009-2013).
Elected by lawyers in the State Bar of Michigan to serve on the Representative Assembly, Cherrin actively participates in making policy for the State Bar of Michigan. As a Law & Media Committee member of the State Bar (2007-2013), Cherrin regularly appeared before organizations seeking media training and other information to help others gain a better understanding of the law in reporting the law. He was named as a Top Lawyer in Detroit (2013) for Government Relations by dbusiness Magazine.
Cherrin has been actively involved with the Multiple Sclerosis Society and served on the MS Society Michigan Chapter Board in 2009-2014. Cherrin leads the MS Society's marketing committee to raise awareness and raise money to find a cure to end MS. He was also the President (2005-2008) of Childhelp, national organization working to meet the physical, emotional, educational and spiritual needs of abused, neglected and at-risk children.
Records are divided into three series: Communications, Finances, and Issues.
Digital records were created and/or maintained by Cherrin during his tenure as Press Secretary and Communications Director for Detroit. The Daniel Cherrin papers document the City of Detroit's and Mayor Ken Cockrel's efforts to move beyond the resignation of Kwame Kilpatrick and promote civic and fiscal responsibility while navigating the larger financial crisis of 2008.
Subjects:
Automobile industry and trade--Michigan.; Cherrin, Daniel.; Cobo Hall (Detroit, Mich.); Detroit (Mich.); Detroit (Mich.)--Politics and government--21st century.; Detroit (Mich.). Mayor.
Contributors:
Cockrel, Kenneth, Jr.
Genre Terms:
Digital file formats.
- Communications
  The Communications series (57.1 MB, 2008-2009) contains materials produced by and about the Cockrel administration, with talking points and speeches related to the opening of a new Census Bureau office, cable commission, Spring Clean Up and Detroit Recycles, and the 2009 State of the City Address as well as articles about Mayor Ken Cockrel's transition and performance, op-ed pieces and news releases produced by the Mayor's office, and snapshots of various pages on the mayor's website as it appeared in 2008-2009. Also includes campaign materials and April 2009 poll results.
  - Articles, Op-Eds, and Website, 2008-2009, .ZIP file
  - Biographies and Campaign Materials, 2008-2009, .ZIP file
  - Talking Points and Speeches, 2009, .ZIP file
  - Other Correspondence, 2008, .ZIP file
- Finances
  The Finances series (10.3 MB, 2008-2009) documents Mayor Ken Cockrel's plans for the City of Detroit's Fiscal Year 2009-2010 budget and includes budget planning documents, press releases and talking points for FY 2009-2010 as well as cash flow records for 2008-2009. Also contains a list of Finance Department accomplishments under Mayor Cockrel.
  - Finances, 2008-2009, .ZIP file
- Issues
  The Issues series (8.8 MB, 2008-2009) documents the Cockrel administration's response to various issues and events, including safety planning for the 2008 Angel's Night (the period from October 29-31, formerly known as Devil's Night, in which 40,000 Detroiters volunteer to promote public safety and prevent acts of vandalism and arson), federal bridge loans to the auto industry (with correspondence to President George W. Bush, Secretary of the Treasury Timothy Geithner, and Director of Recovery for Auto Communities and Workers Ed Montgomery), Cobo Center expansion plans, and Standard & Poor's and Moody's decisions to downgrade the ratings of Detroit's general obligation bonds and unlimited tax debt status.
  - Angel's Night, 2008, .ZIP file
  - Auto Industry Federal Bridge Loan, 2008-2009, .ZIP file
  - Cobo Center Expansion, 2008-2009, .ZIP file
  - Detroit Bond and Credit Rating Downgrade, 2009, .ZIP file